We're now going to look at some additional considerations for ZOS UNIX.
There are several ways to provide print services to an application.
A ZOS UNIX application can use the POSIX functions printf, fprint, write, or fwrite
to place output in the hierarchical file system.
The file can either be specified as standard out or by a file name depending on the function
call used.
The output residing in the file system can be printed by a batch job using dd statements
referring to the out file, by TSOE print options, or by using the lp shell command.
This command dynamically allocates a ZOS sysout data set, opens writes and closes it, and sends
it to the ges pool, which sends it to a printer.
Each ZOS UNIX user has a number of default printers specified in different ways.
The system will select a printer in the following order.
So first of all, the printer in the dest option of the lp shell command or the printf or fprintf
functions.
The printer specified in the lp dest environment variable is next.
And then three, the printer specified in the printer environment variable.
Finally there's four, which is the printer in the rackf user profile.
Currently HFS files are protected with POSIX permission bits.
HFS permission bits allow the installation to specify read authority, write authority, or
search authority for a directory.
They also allow specification of read, write, or execute authority for a file.
Because there are three sets of bits, separate authorities can be specified for the owner
of the file or the directory, the owning group, and everyone else, such as rackf's
Universal Access Authority or UACC.
The owner is represented by a UID, the owning group is represented by a GID.
Access checking compares the user's UID and GID to the one stored in the FSP.
When a security decision is needed, the file system calls rackf and supplies the FSP.
Rackf makes the decision, does any necessary auditing, and returns control back to the
file system.
Rackf does not provide commands to maintain the FSP, but it does provide SAF services
that do the FSP maintenance.
COS Unix provides commands that invoke these SAF services.
Access control lists or ACLs can be used to control access to files and directories
by individual user, UID, and by group, the GID.
ACLs are used along with permission bits.
ACLs are created, modified, and deleted using the setfacl shell command.
The HFS and ZFS file systems support ACLs.
The ACLs are created and checked by rackf, not by the kernel or file system.
There are two kinds of ACL entries.
Base ACL entries are the same as permission bits, so owner, group, and other.
They can be changed using chmod or setfacl.
Extended ACL entries are ACL entries for individual users or groups.
Like the permission bits, they're stored with the file, not in rackf profiles.
Each ACL type, access, file default, and directory default can contain up to 1024 extended ACL entries.
Each extended ACL entry specifies a qualifier to indicate whether the entry pertains to a user or a group,
the actual UID or GID itself, and the permissions being granted or denied by this entry.
The allowable permissions are read, write, and execute.
The commands setfacl and getfacl have been introduced in order to create, modify, and display ACL entries specified by the path,
and here's the syntax for those.
irrska00 is the file checking algorithm.
This callable service has been updated for ACLs and the new UNIX PRIV profiles.
Permissions bits, ACLs, and various UNIX PRIV profiles are used by rackf while performing file access checks.
The rackf basic file checking algorithm checks the owner bits, user ACL entries,
union of group bits, and group ACL entries, and other bits.
Now, it's not always necessary to apply ACLs on every file or directory within a subtree.
If you have a requirement to grant access to an entire subtree, for example, a subtree specific to a given application,
access can be established at the top directory.
If a given user or a group does not have search access to the top directory,
no files within the subtree will be accessible regardless of the permission bit set or ACL contents associated with those files.
The user or the group still needs permission to the files within the directory subtree where appropriate.
If this is already granted by the group or other bits, no ACLs are necessary below the top directory.
In the next video, we'll look at some remaining at ZOS UNIX considerations.